<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shiny Penny</title><link>http://www.shinypenny.org/</link><description>Distraction is us</description><atom:link href="http://www.shinypenny.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2017 &lt;a href="mailto:rod@shinypenny.org"&gt;Rodney Price&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 23:26:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Miles' science fair project</title><link>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/miles-science-fair-project/</link><dc:creator>Rodney Price</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago, I bought a potato gun.  To be more precise, I bought
a kit for a potato gun.  It was well put together, polished even, and
it could shoot a potato a good long way.  I could point it straight
up, shoot the thing, and the potato would go up so far that I would
lose sight of it.  It never hit me on the way down, but it did smack
into the grass with a satisfying thump.  The dog loved it.  So did my
son Miles, then just a few years old.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My wife, on the other hand, was not a fan.  When I knocked a slat out
of the wood fence in the backyard, she was unhappy.  When I shot a
potato into the neighbor's garage door (I really underestimated how
far that thing could shoot) she was really unhappy.  When Miles and I
shot it off in the basement bathroom, my wife and I had a talk.  Miles
and I were both fascinated with the way the potato splattered into
mush when it hit the shower wall.  My wife thought we were down there
tearing the bathroom apart.  Maybe we were.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Soon afterward, the potato gun broke in half.  PVC pipes can only take
so much abuse, it seems.  I put the two halves of the potato gun on a
shelf in the garage and forgot about it.  The level of conflict in my
marriage eased, and all of us went on with our lives.  I had been kind
of an idiot about it, and truth be told, I was a bit relieved.  Funny
how that happens.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Miles, on the other hand, hadn't forgotten.  A few weeks ago, his
teachers at school announced a science fair would be held, and Miles
had an idea.  He would see how far the potato gun would shoot as a
function of elevation and pressure in the chamber.  (The potato gun is
pneumatic, with a pressure gauge and relief valve.  I wasn't being
completely irresponsible, you see.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He got going on this when he read on the internet that the world
record for muzzle velocity of a potato gun was 2,000 and some miles
per hour.  This potato gun, he said, was powered by combustion rather
than compressed air, and he wanted to make one of his own.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I expressed some skepticism that a potato had enough structural
integrity to accelerate to Mach 3 without turning into a fine mist.  I
also made it clear that we weren't going to be building a device using
a possibly uncontrolled explosion to propel a supersonic potato.
Disappointment and some argument ensued.  Miles is now 12 years old,
and as with all 12 year old boys, the thought of explosions and
supersonic anything is magnetic.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We did agree that using my old potato gun for the project might be a
good idea.  It did, after all, have a pressure gauge, and it does
shoot pretty far, satisfying that 12 year old need for speed.  And
destructive power.  If you consider destroying a potato as destructive
power.  So we agreed.  We'd find a big field, and Miles will figure
out a way to measure elevation and distance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now we have some engineering to do.  I'll keep you posted.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/miles-science-fair-project/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 19:57:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Maybe this will work</title><link>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/maybe-this-will-work/</link><dc:creator>Rodney Price</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Hope springs eternal.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/maybe-this-will-work/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 01:08:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>