<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shiny Penny (Posts about radio)</title><link>http://www.shinypenny.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.shinypenny.org/categories/cat_radio.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2017 &lt;a href="mailto:rod@shinypenny.org"&gt;Rodney Price&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 02:30:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A really cheap 433 MHz beacon</title><link>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/a-really-cheap-433-mhz-beacon.html</link><dc:creator>Rodney Price</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.shinypenny.org/images/xy-mk-5v.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Cheap 433 MHz receiver-transmitter pair" src="http://www.shinypenny.org/images/xy-mk-5v.jpg" title="Cheap 433 MHz receiver-transmitter pair" style="float:right;width:35%;margin:10px"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've been having trouble getting the 433 MHz beacon (otherwise known
as the 70 cm beacon) going, so one of our partners Richard suggested
we use a very simple beacon that just needs power and a bit stream.
I've shown a picture of the two at right.  I thought I'd give it a
try, so I bought a few.  Sparkfun was backordered so I searched on
Amazon and found people selling six transmitter-receiver pairs for
$10.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The transmitters are 25 mW at 12V power supply.  We could use a 9V
battery and get 15-20 mW out of it.  I checked the frequency against
the Colorado ham radio &lt;a href="http://shinypenny.org/papers/colorado-70cm-band-plan.pdf"&gt;band plan for 70 cm&lt;/a&gt; (tells you what modulations
are allowed where) and found that 433.92 MHz was right in the middle
of a band where the FCC does not allow repeaters – good for us.
Nothing would infuriate a bunch of hams, and generate complaints to
the FCC, faster than running a beacon on a repeater frequency.  The
transmitter modules are so cheap that their center frequency can drift
over +/- 0.5 MHz, and probably will when the temperature varies.
Fortunately the band is about 1.5 MHz wide.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/a-really-cheap-433-mhz-beacon.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>balloon</category><category>beacon</category><category>radio</category><guid>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/a-really-cheap-433-mhz-beacon.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 03:51:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>70cm beacon progress</title><link>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/70cm-beacon-progress.html</link><dc:creator>Rodney Price</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.shinypenny.org/images/balloon/434-mhz-wireless-transceiver-rfm69hcw.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="My first try at soldering a transmitter" src="http://www.shinypenny.org/images/balloon/434-mhz-wireless-transceiver-rfm69hcw.jpg" title="My first try at soldering a transmitter" style="float:left;width:35%;margin:10px"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're putting two radios on the high-altitude balloon, just to have a
backup in case one of them fails.  We're pretty confident that the 
balloon will fly, but we'd like to get it back, and radio beacons are
the best way to do that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Soldering tiny little parts can be painful – especially when you
really would prefer not to fry your part with too much heat.  Such was
the case when I tried to attach wires to the 70 cm transmitter modules
I had bought for the balloon.  You can see one of them in the picture
with the quarter, to the left.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And I had bought two of them, just in case!  Normally, you solder to
these things using a header, which has pins every 0.1 inches.  Not
this thing.  It had to have them every 2 mm.  Just different enough to
make things difficult.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So I fried two of them, so badly that I actually cracked several of
the parts on the boards in pieces.  For those of you who've never
soldered electronic parts before, that's really bad.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was in college, I had a summer job soldering electronic parts 8
hours a day.  I got pretty good at it, I thought.  Maybe not so much.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/70cm-beacon-progress.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>balloon</category><category>radio</category><guid>http://www.shinypenny.org/posts/70cm-beacon-progress.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 23:07:37 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>